<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two consolatory letters written to the right honorable the Countess of Westmorland The first upon the occasion of the death of Sr Roger Townshend, Baronet: the second upon the death of Mrs Anne Cartwright, Her Honour's children by Sir Roger Townshend, Baronet, her former husband.</title>
            <author>Hodges, Thomas, d. 1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2324B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218018</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829646</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829646</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34089</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44075)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34089)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2007:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two consolatory letters written to the right honorable the Countess of Westmorland The first upon the occasion of the death of Sr Roger Townshend, Baronet: the second upon the death of Mrs Anne Cartwright, Her Honour's children by Sir Roger Townshend, Baronet, her former husband.</title>
                  <author>Hodges, Thomas, d. 1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2, 5-32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A. Maxwell, for Samuel Gellibrand at the Golden Ball in St. Paul's Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Each letter signed by Thomas Hodges.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect? Pgs. 2 and 3 lacking or not microfilmed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Westmorland, Mary Fane, --  Countess of, ca. 1611-1669.</term>
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34089:1"/>
            <p>Two Conſolatory LETTERS Written to the RIGHT HONORABLE THE COUNTESS OF Weſtmorland.</p>
            <p>The firſt upon occaſion of the death of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>ROGER TOWNSHEND,</hi> Baronet:</p>
            <p>The Second upon the death of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>ANNE CARTWRIGHT,</hi> Her Honour's Children by Sir <hi>ROGER TOWNSHEND</hi> Baronet, her former Husband.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Maxwel,</hi> for <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL GELLIBRAND,</hi> at the Golden Ball in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church yard. 1669.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:34089:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:34089:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable Lady, THE LADY MARY, COUNTESS OF <hi>WESTMORLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Doctrine of the vanity of the leſſer World [Man], and of the greater World unto Man, here preſented unto your Ladiſhips hands, hath been from Heaven, with ſound of Drum and Trumpet, preached, yea proclaimed in your ears, and the ears of this whole Nation, now, for above ſeven years together.</p>
            <p>And if Warr, that <hi>Boanerges,</hi> or Thundering Preacher, at your very door had not ſpoken loud enough to be heard, God hath by a ſad hand of his Providence, written the ſame Leſſon in very legible Characters to your Ladiſhip from beyond the Seas. [Fear not, Madam, I beſeech you, to read on; the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34089:3"/>deſign of this Epiſtle is not to renew your grief, but to promote or perpetuate your joy rather.] You have had the delight of your eyes, the joy of your heart, the Heir and Glory of your Houſe, your dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Son, Sir <hi>Roger Townſhend,</hi> (whoſe memory is and ſhall be precious) about his beſt Eſtate, and in the very Spring and Flower of his Age, cropt off by the hand of Death in a ſtrange Land; of whom I had almoſt ſaid, (alluding to that of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil. 3.4.5.) <hi>That if any man thinketh that he hath whereof he might truſt in the fleſh,</hi> (to ſay wherefore he ſhould not be made ſubject unto Vanity, but be priviledged from the Arreſt of Death) <hi>He more.</hi> A Gentleman nobly deſcended, of a large Eſtate, very good Parts, much Ingenuity, and remarkable Piety.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhall not take upon me the Office of an <hi>Herauld,</hi> to <hi>blazon</hi> his <hi>Coat,</hi> and tell who he was among the Great Men of the World; but of a <hi>Divine</hi> rather, in ſome meaſure, to <hi>Anatomize</hi> his heart, and ſhew what he was amongſt good men, and towards God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> The Days, the Years of Mourning for your deceaſed Son, are paſt: (and God hath ſince gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you many Sons in place of him whom He took) And therefore, I hope, the mentioning of his <hi>death,</hi> ſhall not revive your former ſorrows, to endanger your <hi>life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he was in <hi>France,</hi> I remember your Ladiſhip took pleaſure in having his <hi>Picture</hi> by you, which was ſent you from thence. Now that he is gone to <hi>Heaven,</hi> give me leave, I pray you, to endeavour to deſcribe what manner of Man he was as to his better part (his Soul, I mean) even when he was here upon <hi>Earth.</hi> The <hi>Picture</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:34089:3"/>of his <hi>Piety,</hi> will, I humbly conceive, be no ſmall <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> to your Ladiſhip, a great <hi>Ornament</hi> to the Houſe, and an excellent <hi>Pattern</hi> and <hi>Copy</hi> to the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, without further Preface, As <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren ſaid to their Father <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 37.32. <hi>This have we found; know now, whether it be thy Sons Coat, or no.</hi> So ſay I, This have I found, looking in my Memory; Know now whether it be your Son's <hi>Picture,</hi> or no.</p>
            <p>I begin with his <hi>Religion,</hi> there where uſually <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> begins. He was a careful obſerver of the <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath,</hi> attending diligently upon the publike Ordinances; ſometimes hearing Three, but conſtantly Two Sermons in a Day, and often ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Notes: A practiſe before his time but ſomewhat rare in <hi>Cambridg,</hi> among Students of his Rank.</p>
            <p>Nor did his <hi>Sabbath</hi> end with the publike ſolemn Service; He was devout at home, as well as at Church: He was one of the chief Inſtruments to ſet up and countenance that good Cuſtom in the Colledg, of meeting together on the Lord's-day-night, after Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to pray, ſing, and repeat the Sermon in their Chambers; and this at a time when it was ſo ſtrange and unwelcome to ſome profane ſpirits thereabouts, that I remember once there was a Brick-bat thrown in at the Window amongſt them, where, and whilſt they were at Prayers together. He kept a watch over the door of his lips on that day, leſt his words ſhould be either of worldly buſineſſes or recreations; and for this reaſon he would then often take his Commons in his Chamber, rather than in the Colledg-Hall, leſt there in a mixt company he ſhould be put upon Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34089:4"/>or Queſtions unſuitable for that Day.</p>
            <p>His manner was to approach the Lord's Table not without ſolemn preparation: for which work he did not only allot himſelf, but allow his Servants alſo convenient time on the Week-days. And beſides the examination of his own Conſcience, he ſubmitted himſelf to be examined by Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> before his firſt admiſſion to the Sacrament with his Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and having once a door opened to that Ordinance, he would afterwards ſo caſt his Journeys to <hi>London,</hi> (if it might be) as to be there on the day of their Monthly Sacrament, to be a Gueſt at the Lord's Table; at which times (when he could not be with your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip) he would chuſe ſuch Lodgings as where he thought he might enjoy God, his Sabbaths, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, beſt.</p>
            <p>Nor was all his Devotion confined to the Weekly-Sabbath only. He was alſo a Religious obſerver of Days of publike Faſts or Humiliation; and of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Feaſts or Rejoycing, which ſome call <hi>Sabbaths extraordinary.</hi> I remember that when once upon a Day of Thankſgiving, he was deſired to go to Bowls, he did out of Conſcience refuſe it, though it were (if I miſtake not) after the Ordinances were done in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and though thereunto deſired by a Noble Friend, and in very civil company.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe publike ſolemn times of Worſhip, both ordinary, and extraordinary; he would ſometimes keep a private Faſt by himſelf in his Chamber. I remember he kept one once at <hi>Cambridg,</hi> for to humble his ſoul for the ſins of his Thoughts, and particularly of his Dreams.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I have ſhewed you, <hi>Madam,</hi> your Son's
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34089:4"/>
               <hi>Picture</hi> one way only, as it reſpects God, looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: Will you ſee it another way, as it looks down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards man? Come and ſee.</p>
            <p>He was a lover of good men; of thoſe, he choſe his Intimates. A lover particularly of Good Miniſters; to thoſe he gave hopes of being a good Friend and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, now in a time when they have many great Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and but few real and powerful Friends. How willing was he to have trod in thoſe good ſteps of his deceaſed Father, To have given the Impropriate Tythes of <hi>Rudham,</hi> to make a conſiderable mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for a good Miniſter?</p>
            <p>He was charitable, not to ſay bountiful, to them that ſtood in need: I remember once at <hi>Raynham,</hi> he gave ten ſhillings to a poor old man of the Town that came to ſee him. And when he left the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, he gave a Penſion or Allowance of ten or twelve pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> to a poor Scholar who had waited on him there: of which charitable act, as well as of his Lands, his loving Brother,
<note n="*" place="margin">Now Lord <hi>Townſhend.</hi>
               </note> Sir <hi>Horatio Townſhend,</hi> became Heir, continuing the Penſion or Exhibition af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his deceaſe. Nor was he likely, as the Proverb is, <hi>To rob</hi> Peter <hi>to pay</hi> Paul, (as too many do unjuſtly, taking from ſome, whilſt they pretend charitably to give to others) of this I conceive he gave ſome proof once in a journey towards <hi>London,</hi> when he was earneſt to have ſent his man back to make ſatisfaction for our riding over the Corn, in a place where the High-way was foul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> You have ſeen your Son's Image and Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, what manner of man he was at Church and abroad. Will you but behold him in his Chamber, and in his Cloſet?</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:34089:5"/>
            <p> He had learnt betimes to cry <hi>Abba</hi> Father in ſecret, and to pray frequently and fervently even without a Book.</p>
            <p>Nor was he aſhamed to pray, upon good occaſion, with his own Family, (ſo I call the company he had about him at <hi>Cambridg</hi>) and not to ſerve God only by a <hi>Proxie.</hi> He ſeemed to me to affect and countenance that Servant moſt, who he thought loved and ſerved his Heavenly Maſter beſt.</p>
            <p>He uſed, at night, to reflect upon what had paſſed him in the day-time; and frequently took private Notes thereof before he ſlept.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> This was your Son before, and whilſt he was a Student in the Colledg. This was his Idea or Picture at ſeventeen or eighteen years of age.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, <hi>Had this fair face no ſpot? Had this body no ſhadow accompanying it? Or is it wanting in the Picture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer: Yes, he had: and this Piece had a dark ſide as well as a bright. He was naturally too too paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate; and for this cauſe upon occaſion of ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitancy that way, I remember that once at <hi>London,</hi> before he came to the Univerſity, I found him in his Cloſet very ſad and penſive. Hereupon, with much ado, and great importunity, I prevailed with him to tell me what he was thinking of, which did ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him. It was this: He was wiſhing or deſiring that God would take him out of the world, for he feared he ſhould never be able to maſter his paſſions.</p>
            <p>Again, he was much troubled at <hi>Cambridg,</hi> (as many of the dear ſervants of God have been) with horrid blaſphemous thoughts. And although theſe monſtrous Conceptions were rather, I conceive, the Devil's Brats,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34089:5"/>and to be laid at his door; yet for theſe would he cry bitterly, and be almoſt in <hi>Rachel's</hi> ſad poſture, refuſing to be comforted.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, He was overſcrupulous: he had a <hi>tender</hi> Conſcience, and a <hi>ſorupulous</hi> Conſcience. <hi>That</hi> was his glory. <hi>This</hi> his trouble. Yet, ſcruples I have heard well compared to Nettles; which although they are not good in themſelves, yet they are a ſign of a good Soil where they grow.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Madam,</hi> if the ſight of your Son in a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful and weeping poſture, ſhould by ſympathy put your Ladiſhip into the like; if your eyes ſhould affect your heart; and again, your heart fill your eyes: give me leave to comfort you before I leave you, who am he who hath made you ſorrowful in this Epiſtle. If this ſorry <hi>Pourtraiture,</hi> laid in Water-colours by me, cauſe your grief; yet let the Ointment and Perfume of your Son's Good Name, wrapt up in this Paper, (and his Goodneſs and Vertue here ſhadowed forth, which deſerved to have been laid in Oyl, and to be had in everlaſting remembrance) rejoice your heart.</p>
            <p>The truth is, it would be your ſin to ſorrow for ſuch a Son, as one that hath no hope. His Body ſleeps in Jeſus in the Earth; and his Soul wakes with Jeſus in the Heavens: and when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall come again, him will God bring with him. Wherefore, <hi>Comfort your ſelf with theſe words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Could you bear his abſence when he was at <hi>Paris,</hi> and cannot now he is in <hi>Paradice?</hi> Might he go to ſee <hi>Rome,</hi> and may he not go to poſſeſs <hi>Heaven?</hi> Would you conſent or connive at his going to ſee another <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> (ſo the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>John, Rev.</hi> chap. 17, and 18. and the holy Father <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in his City, <hi>viz. l.</hi> 16.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34089:6"/>c. 17. calls <hi>Rome</hi>) and muſt not he travel to <hi>Heaven,</hi> that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is above, the Mother of us all?</p>
            <p>I know there is a great <hi>Chaſme</hi> of diſtance 'twixt him and you; now he is in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and you are upon <hi>Earth.</hi> Yet let me tell you, You do not know but that every day you may ſee him; you may look daily to be called to go to him. But when he was beyond Seas, you could not daily expect his return to you. Nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are you at ſo great a diſtance now from him, but that you may once a day, yea oftentimes every day, look out and ſee the place where your Son is. You may ſee, without a Proſpective or Teleſcope, as it were, the Foundations of that glorious City, and the Floor and Pavement of that Royal Palace, which muſt contain him till you come to him.</p>
            <p>We read, <hi>Matt.</hi> 2.9, 10. when the wiſe men ſaw the Starr ſtanding over the place where the young Child was, <hi>they rejoyced with exceeding great joy.</hi> As often as you lift up your eyes to <hi>Heaven,</hi> and ſee ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sun, Moon, or any of the Starrs, you ſee them under the place where your Child, where your Son is, (yea, and where your Saviour is) yea, where he ſhines as the Sun in the Kingdom of his Father; and therefore rejoyce and be exceeding glad.</p>
            <p>You and your Son are ſtill both (as it were) of one and the ſame <hi>Houſe,</hi> namely, retainers to one and the ſame Lord: I confeſs he is preferred before you his Mother, he is firſt taken up to ſerve above Stairs in the Chamber of Preſence, to wait continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, to behold the Lord and Maſter face to face alway. Your Ladiſhip, though a Servant and Handmaid to the ſame Lord, yet muſt wait below Stairs, fitting your ſelf, and expecting till you ſhall be called up.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:34089:6"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Madam,</hi> You deem it an honour to be called a Daughter of <hi>Abraham;</hi> why then ſhould you be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to part with your Son, your dearly beloved Son, when God calls for him? So was not <hi>Abraham.</hi> Hereby ſhall it be known that you love God, if you ſhall not (no not in your heart) withhold or recall your Son, your dear Son, (as one too dear) from him who hath given your Ladiſhip twenty Sons and Daughters; yea, God hath given you his own Son, though an only Son, the dearly beloved of his Soul, out of his boſome: Why ſhould not he have yours? His Son was the Heir of the World, the Heir of all things, and yet He gave him you freely, and for your ſake, and for your Son's ſake, to become poor, and to be made a Man of ſorrows, and acquainted with griefs: Why ſhould you withhold in your heart your Son, though your Heir, when He calls for him out of the World, this valley of tears, to a Kingdom, to a Throne, to wipe all tears from his eyes, and to have his head crowned, his heart filled with joy unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and full of glory.</p>
            <p>If one Member be honoured or rejoyce, all the Members rejoyce with it. If your Son, ſo conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a part of your ſelf, come to honour, why do you not acknowledg it? Why do you not rejoyce toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him?</p>
            <p>I find <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.27. that <hi>Laban</hi> chides <hi>Jacob</hi> his Son-in-law, for ſtealing and carrying away his Daughters as Captives, ſaying, he would have ſent him away with mirth, and with Songs, and with Tabrel, and with Harps, when he was returning home to the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> Let your Son go to the Heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:34089:7"/>Let his ſoul return home to his own Countrey, and his Father's Houſe; ſend him not away with bitter cryes and tears; but rather with mirth and ſongs, with Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brel and Harp.</p>
            <p>What joy, muſick, and dancing, do we read of at the return of the Prodigal (who had been ſpiritually dead, namely, in his ſins and treſpaſſes, but was now alive) becauſe he had part in the firſt Reſurrection. We read of no ſuch joy, no ſuch muſick and dancing, at the raiſing up of <hi>Lazarus</hi> out of the Grave. Let this teach you, that your joy for your Son's having part in the firſt Reſurrection, and thereby having paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from death to life, ſo that the ſecond death on him can have no power, ſhould moderate your ſorrow for his going thorough the valley of the ſhadow of death, in ſuch Company too, as that you need fear none evil; for God is with him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>If there was joy in Heaven among the holy Angels, at his firſt converſion from being a Sinner to a Saint, (as ſure there was) let not there be immoderate ſorrow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, at his tranſlation from amongſt Sinners, to Saints and Angels, to rejoice together with them; yea, into his Maſter's Joy.</p>
            <p>Could the Saints in Heaven ſympathize with their Friends ſorrows on Earth, the Mother's Grief would eclipſe the Son's Joy. All tears would never be wiped from his Eyes, ſo long as there were any in yours His Joy would not be full, ſo long as your Sorrows over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed are the dead that dye in the Lord,</hi> is a true and faithful ſaying in the moſt Golden Age, and moſt <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon</hi> days in the World. How bleſſed is he then that <hi>dyed in the Lord,</hi> and in peace on his bed, in an Iron Age, in times of War and Blood.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:34089:7"/>
            <p> In ſuch times of publike Calamity, there is a Wo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in Scripture to them that are with Child, or give ſuck, in thoſe days: but no where do we read of any wo to them whoſe Children God <hi>takes to himſelf from the evil to come</hi> in thoſe days.</p>
            <p>It may be you ſay in your heart, <hi>Had he dyed in his own Countrey, at home, then you could have born it; but this doth imbitter your grief, That he dyed in his travel, and in a ſtrange Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> He had done ſo, if he had returned hither, and dyed at home; if in his own Land, in his own Houſe, and upon his own Bed, he had been but a <hi>ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and pilgrim, as all his fathers were.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had he returned to <hi>England,</hi> where would he have had meet Companions of his Age and Piety? Had he gone to <hi>Rome,</hi> I believe he would ſcarce have found one like himſelf. In Heaven he was matched as ſoon as ever he came thither, and that of his Countrey-men: There's the good King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, and the good Lord <hi>Harrington,</hi> young men, famous for Vertue and Piety in their generation.</p>
            <p>Again, Your Son had as ſhort and ſafe a paſſage to Heaven from <hi>Geneva,</hi> as he could have had from his own Houſe at <hi>Raynham.</hi> And though his Corps came not to the Sepulchers of his Fathers, yet he lies interr'd and intomb'd with honour, near the Noble and Pious Marqueſs of <hi>Vico,</hi> and not far from the Holy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Calvin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He dyed far abſent from his dear Mother, and many of his Noble Friends; yet he dyed in the Houſe of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Diodate.</hi> In the preſence of his very lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and only Brother, was brought to his Grave with very great ſolemnity and honour, and lieth intombed in <hi>Geneva;</hi> a City, for <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> one of the moſt famous throughout the World.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:34089:8"/>
            <p> Thus far I have endeavoured to comfort your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip: but to deal plainly with you, If the days and years of your mourning ſhould not be paſt, I muſt (as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſometimes in another caſe did) wax very bold, and chide you.</p>
            <p>It is very obſervable, how God takes up <hi>Samuel,</hi> though a Prophet, a man of God, for his exceſſive mourning for the caſting off of <hi>Saul,</hi> ſaying to him, <hi>How long wilt thou mourn for Saul, ſeeing I have reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him?</hi> And may not I in like manner ſay to you, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing for your Son advanced to an Eternal Kingdom, (ſurely you may believe God doth) <hi>How long wilt thou mourn for thy Son, ſeeing I have received him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſay more? I wiſh I have not ſaid too much already, namely, that which may trouble you, whilſt it was mine endeavour to comfort you. Pray <hi>Madam</hi> be comforted. Pray <hi>Madam</hi> comfort your ſelf. Take the ſame courſe to comfort your ſelf now he is gone home, which I ſuppoſe you did when he was in his Travels abroad: Read over his Letters, Diſcourſes, Meditations, or any thing of his by you. In theſe (as it is ſaid of <hi>Abel</hi>) <hi>he being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</hi> And thus you may converſe with him ſtill, and as long as you live.</p>
            <p>And, if your Ladiſhip pleaſe, pray ſometimes at your leiſure look upon this Epiſtle: it is (though not a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from him, yet) a kind of Letter of, or concerning him; or if you will, herein you have his Image and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription; here you have his Picture to the life, what manner of man he was when at <hi>Cambridg.</hi> And <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> this Letter tells you (or here you may read) your Son is well; your Son liveth; he is happie, and his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie is bleſſed: and I wiſh all the Friends of Sir <hi>Roger Townſhend,</hi> when they die, may be as <hi>this young man is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for your Ladiſhip, eſpecially, my Prayer is, <hi>That
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34089:8"/>the conſolations of the Almighty may not ſeem ſmall unto you; and that the God and Father of all conſolations, would fill you with everlaſting conſolation, and good hope through grace, and fill you with all joy and peace in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, that ſince he may not come to you while you live, you may go to him when you dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if any ſhould blame me for commemorating the dead, ſo as I have done in this Epiſtle, ſaying, <hi>the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of the ſhadow of death, is and ought to be in the Land of forgetfulneſs:</hi> I appeal to the parallel practiſe of holy men of God recorded in the Sacred Scripture, for my juſtification. There I find <hi>David,</hi> a man after Gods own heart, making honourable mention of <hi>Saul,</hi> and of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan,</hi> preſently after their death, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.17. And (if ſome of the Learned judg aright upon v. 18.) taking order to perpetuate their memory to ſucceeding gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. There I meet with the commemoration of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Samuel, Pſal.</hi> 99.26. and of <hi>Noah,</hi> and <hi>Job,</hi> a good while after they were dead. And laſtly, there's a ſolemn commemoration of <hi>Joſiab,</hi> of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to after-ages, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35 25, 26.</p>
            <p>But if on the other ſide, any Friend ſhould be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at my remembring him whom they could never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, ſaying at my pouring out of this Box of precious Ointment of his good Name on him, <hi>Wherefore is this loſs?</hi> My anſwer to ſuch is, That thoſe devout Women who prepared Spices and Odours to perfume our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's dead body, which, it was decreed, ſhould not ſee corruption, (as well as ſhe that poured on him a Box of coſtly Ointment whilſt alive) have all their Piety re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to their praiſe, in the Goſpel, to this day.</p>
            <p>I hope the good name and bleſſed memory of Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Townſhend,</hi> ſhall never ſee corruption, (for, <hi>the name of the wicked ſhall rot, but the righteous ſhall be bad in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34089:9"/>everlaſting remembrance</hi>) yet I deem it a friendly office, and ſuch a practice as maybe pardoned, for one that had once the honour of ſuch a Pupil, at leaſt to perfume your Ladiſhips Cloſet with your Son's ſweet Name, and gracious odoriferous qualities ſent you in this Paper. And again, I ſay, I have done it for his burial, that is, I humbly preſent your Ladiſhip with this Piece, as a Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral-Sermon for your Son Sir <hi>Roger Townſhend,</hi> for ſo the manner of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> is to bury.</p>
            <p>What pity is it that the light of his good example, ſhould be put under a buſhel, or put out in obſcurity by his death, and not rather be ſet up in a Candleſtick to give light to all that are in the houſe?</p>
            <p>Truly my deſire is, by this means, (if the will of God be ſo) to provoke to emulation chiefly all young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, eſpecially thoſe of his Kindred, Friends, and Acquaintance, and to ſave ſome, yea, all of them.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall leave praiſing of the dead, and betake my ſelf to my prayers for the living: And for this cauſe <hi>I bow my knees to the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, of whom the whole Family in Heaven and Earth is named, That he would grant, that that unfeigned faith which dwelt firſt in his Grandmother the Lady</hi> Vere, <hi>and in your Ladiſhip his dear Mother, (in you ſtill growing up to a full Aſſurance) and I am perſwaded in him alſo (in whom it is already changed into Viſion and Fruition) may be intailed and doubled upon his rightful Heir, and only Brother,
<note n="*" place="margin">Now Lord <hi>Townſhend.</hi>
                  </note> Sir</hi> Horatio Townſhend, <hi>and all of that Race and Family, their Noble Kindred and Allies, and that there may not want a man of the Houſe of the</hi> Townſhends <hi>to ſtand for and before the Lord for ever.</hi> So prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>Your Honour's very humble Servant, in and for the Lord, <hi>Thomas Hedges.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:34089:9"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE COUNTESSE OF <hi>WESTMORLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FOraſmuch as Womens Names are ſwallowed up in the Names of their Husbands, whilſt they live; (whence amongſt the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> Women have a Name ſignifying <hi>Forgetfulneſs</hi>) and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as your deceaſed Daughter, Mrs. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> hath left two Children behind her ſo young, that 'tis impoſſible they ſhould ever remember their dear Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Face; Give me leave to endeavour to preſerve ſome memories of her, and to ſet them before the eyes (at leaſt) of thoſe little ones, in time to come, that they may learn to write after her Copy, and be known to be her Children by imitation of her Vertues, as well as by participating of her Likeneſs.</p>
            <p>Your Ladiſhip may be pleaſed to remember, I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34089:10"/>the like Repreſentation of your dear Son, her Brother, (my Pupil) Sir <hi>Roger Townſhend,</hi> of bleſſed memory, many years ſince: and now my humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt is, That your Ladiſhip would favour my preſent Eſſay for your lately deceaſed Daughter, Mrs. <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> my Neighbour; that I may not ſeparate the Brother and Siſter dead; who as they were one in a holy life, ſo now after their death they are not divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. She her ſelf was pleaſed with the reading of the Lives of others, though ſtrangers to her; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope your Ladiſhip will not be diſpleaſed at my writing ſomething of hers, your ſo near a Relation. I know ſhe was a Woman ſubject to like paſſions with other Women, breeding Women, and perhaps more than many others; yet ſhe knew it, and, I am inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, prayed againſt it, and had got ground of it: Yet this I can ſay, and ſay truly of her, That though ſhe loſt Eight Children, and four of them Sons; yet I do not remember that ever I heard her, though often <hi>grieve,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>groan,</hi> yet never to <hi>grumble</hi> againſt the Divine Majeſty: and yet I muſt ſay of her, Her love to her Children was wonderfully, paſſing the love of moſt Women: I have heard her ſay, <hi>I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have Children without Land, than Land without Children.</hi> 'Tis true, ſhe had a <hi>great</hi> ſpirit, and a <hi>good</hi> ſpirit alſo; for ſhe would be hot and zealous for God, his Glory, Worſhip, People, and Intereſt, in the world, as well as in her own Cauſe and Concernment; and that at a time when others who had been ſcalding hot, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved luke-warm, if not key-cold, in Religion.</p>
            <p>In the ninth Chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, we read it an Argument or Evidence of that cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Veſſel of our Lord, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34089:10"/>
               <hi>Behold he prayeth;</hi> and let me ſay, Behold a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Abraham,</hi> behold a Servant, an Handmaid of the Lord, for behold ſhe prayed; ſhe had learned to cry daily, <hi>Abba</hi> Father, and ſometimes to offer up ſtrong cries, with prayers and tears, to him that was able to ſanctifie and ſave her: Pray ſhe could, and did, both in the Church, in the Family, in her Cloſet: ſhe ſerved God alone, and with others; ſhe was not above Forms, nor under them; but could join in prayer either with, or without a Book, as occaſion ſerved. She was a Friend to <hi>extraordinary</hi> times of Prayer, as well as <hi>ordinary.</hi> Once before her Lying-in, ſhe ſent a Letter, and a Meſſenger, (a Miniſter) to crave the Biſhops leave to have a Faſt in her Houſe, to beg Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in her extremitie: and though ſhe could pray well her ſelf, and did uſe to do ſo with her Maids and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren on the Lord's Day; yet ſhe did not diſdain to deſire the aſſiſtance of other Womens prayers, though her Inferiors, with her, and for her: and as the Angel ſaid to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> ſo may I ſay of her, <hi>That her Prayers and her Alms were come up before God.</hi> As ſhe was one that did ask Mercy of God, ſo ſhe was one that did ſhew Mercy to the Poor. She made conſtant proviſion twice a week, of Meat, Bread, and Broath, for the Poor of the Town where ſhe lived. She would viſit the Poor when ſick, and would afford them her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and Cordials too, for their recovery. She would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that the Poor might have the help both of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and Doctor, the Soul and Body-Phyſician both. When there was occaſion, (as often there was) to ſend for Doctors from <hi>Oxford,</hi> for her Children; ſhe would make it her buſineſs to plead the Cauſe of the Poor that were ſick in the Town and procured ſometimes as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34089:11"/>good Advice for them for nothing, as ſhe had her ſelf for Fees: Nor yet did the Doctors loſe all their Alms this way; for ſhe had ſuch an excellent Receit-Book, or Store-houſe of Remedies, that ſhe could and did thence ſometimes impart to the Phyſicians as good Counſel as they gave their Patients either with or without a Fee.</p>
            <p>And here give me leave to tell your Ladiſhip what a Student your Daughter was in the beſt of Receit-Books, the Book of Books, the Holy Bible: Out of this <hi>Diſpenſatory,</hi> as the Learned Scribe out of his Treaſure, ſhe could bring things new and old: Salves for the worſt, that is, Soul-Diſeaſes. She was a daily reader, and due reverencer of the Sacred Scripture. She was ſo great a Proficient in it, that ſhe could di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe of the Hiſtory, argue about the Points of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine contained, and matter of Duties required in it, with Miniſters and Doctors. She was a Champion for the Truth, and was able to chuſe ſuch ſmooth Stones out of this pure Criſtal Brook, the Holy Scripture, and to ſling them ſo, as to ſtrike the ſtouteſt <hi>Goliah</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Philiſtines</hi> in the fore-head. When once there was a diſcourſe with a <hi>Papiſt</hi> concerning the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of Prieſts Marriage, how quickly and appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely did ſhe alledg that of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, A Biſhop muſt be the Husband of one Wife,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.2. Had ſhe lived in former Ages, ſhe might better for her knowledg have been admitted into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, than thoſe Women we read of in our Church-Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, and particularly, in Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> his <hi>Conc. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>She was zealous for the Honour and Authority of the Holy Scripture; ſhe liked not that Wits ſhould
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34089:11"/>ſhew their folly, as many too too often do, in carping at, and criticizing againſt the Contents of it. When any Queſtion in Religion was moved or ſtarted, ſhe would appeal from Man's Teſtimony, to God's; and would have it tried and judged by that: and as of old they uſed to ask Counſel at <hi>Abel,</hi> and ſo end the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or Controverſie; ſo was ſhe for having all diſputes in Religion to be decided by the Scripture; to ask Counſel at that, and ſo to end the Matter or Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie. She had her Senſes exerciſed to diſcern betwixt Truth and Falſhood, 'twixt good and bad Doctrine. Her Ear could taſt words, whether ſound or unſound, as her Pallat meats, whether ſavoury or unſavoury; and having taſted the goodneſs of true Religion, ſhe could be zealous for it. I remember once I being in diſpute with a <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> and he charging me to be hot; ſhe ſtanding by, replied ſuddenly, <hi>Why ſhould not he be as zealous for his Religion, as you are for yours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you ask me how ſhe came to be mighty in the Scriptures, with <hi>Apollos,</hi> and to know the way of God ſo perfectly with <hi>Aquilla</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla?</hi> I anſwer, Her delight was in the Law of God, and in that did ſhe read day and night. She ſpent more time daily in adorning her Soul, than her Body; and made more uſe of the Scriptures, than of any other Mirrour whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. She did write many Volumes of Sermons, which ſhe heard preached; and ſhe read many Printed ones, and other Treatiſes of Divinity, which ſhe bought. Her daily converſe was with good Chriſtians, and good Books: the Lord's Day ſhe made a Market-day for her ſoul; a Feaſt, a good day for her ſoul. She made Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſpending the Lord's Day, and would be troubled when hindred from a ſpiritual improvement
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34089:12"/>of it, and complain at night ſhe had loſt a day. She ſcrupled unneceſſary ſending her Servants abroad on that day, or uncharitable keeping them at home, and debarring them the liberty of hearing God's Word. She offered the ſacrifice of Prayer for her Children, like <hi>Job.</hi> Reſolved, that no ungodly, ſwearing, or drunken perſons, ſhould tarry in her houſe, like <hi>David.</hi> And again, with <hi>Joſhua,</hi> That ſhe and her Houſe would ſerve the Lord. She was for the Marrow, Quinteſſence, the Life and Soul of Religion; not only zealous for or againſt Ceremonies, but for the ſubſtance of God's Worſhip and Service. She had, I think, a good, if not the beſt temper, <hi>viz.</hi> an indifferent temper as to things indifferent in Religion. She refuſed not to hear Divine Service read, though in a Surplice; nor a Biſhop preach, though in a <hi>Rochet:</hi> and yet was not for perſecuting thoſe who really ſcrupled either; having a tender Conſcience her ſelf, though not a ſcrupulous one. She was very tender of preſſing upon others Conſciences. She was not like thoſe narrow Souls, who like or love none but of their own Way or Party, Humour or Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: but had a general kindneſs for good Chriſtians of all Perſwaſſons. She loved indeed ſound, ſolid, and affectionate Preaching: ſhe liked not a Miniſter ſhould freeze in his Study all the Week, and ſweat in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit on the Lord's Day; nor that he ſhould ſweat in his Study, and freeze in the Pulpit; nor without good reaſon: for that which comes from the heart, is moſt likely to go to the heart; and he that is moſt perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of, and affected with what he ſpeaks himſelf, is moſt likely to perſwade and affect others. And as ſhe had choſen her daily-walk in the King of Heaven's High-way, her ſelf; ſo did ſhe deſire not to go alone,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34089:12"/>but in company, and in the company of her neareſt Relations, Children, and Servants. She taught her Daughter, that was capable of learning, the fear of the Lord, to read the Scriptures, to learn her Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, to pray betimes: and ſhe made it her great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt upon her Death-bed, That her Children might be brought up religiouſly, and diſpoſed of, (when fit for marriage) rather into <hi>good,</hi> than <hi>great</hi> Families. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was alive in her, and ſhe was not willing it ſhould dye with her, but be propagated and flouriſh in the Family when ſhe was dead.</p>
            <p>She profeſſed a great love to Truth: and 'tis the Character which the God of Truth gives to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, They will not lye, though they be belyed by the Father of Lyes, and falſly reported of to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The Law of Chaſtity was in her Looks, and in her Lips: I never heard an obſcene impure word come out of her Lips. She could bluſh for other Women, that could not for themſelves. Her care was for her ſelf, and her counſel to others, To avoid not only <hi>ſhame,</hi> but <hi>blame;</hi> and not only all faults, but ſuſpition; and not only to do no evil, but not to be thought to do any. She uſed neither Art nor Sin, to make her appear beautiful; nor any rich and coſtly attire, to make her brave. Her Apparel and Dreſs was rather below, than above her Eſtate and Quality.</p>
            <p>She was a lover of her Friends, and would deny her ſelf, to ſerve and help them. She would own a Friend in Adverſity. She was not as many great ones are, ſo high as to deſpiſe a Relation in a low eſtate: and had it been as much in her Power, as it was in her Will, there ſhould no Friend have ſtood in need of any other but her ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:34089:13"/>
            <p> She was Generous and Noble, and loved Hoſpitality and Bounty. She kept an Houſe for ordinaries and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinaries (all things conſidered) far beyond many her Equals and Superiors in Eſtate, and yet did not undo her ſelf or Husband. It was a declared Maxim of hers, which ſhe experimented in part her ſelf, <hi>That good Houſe-keeping undoes no body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was uſed to reward well thoſe who did ought for her; and ſhe was charitable to, and beyond her power, to thoſe who could do nothing but pray for her. If it had pleaſed God ſhe had come to that great Eſtate to which ſhe was (I may ſay) contracted by her marriage to the Heir of it, ſhe had a Principle (which put in practice, as 'tis not to be doubted but it would) of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Conſcience to reward old Servants. I remember her alledging that place in diſcourſe to that purpoſe, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſend him away empty,</hi> Deut. 15.12, 13. The deſire of her ſoul was towards God, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his Holineſs. She deſired to fear God's Name, and delighted in them that feared him. Her great deſign and aim was, to ſerve God, and ſave her ſoul: and though ſhe had her weakneſſes and failings, as the Moon hath her ſpots; yet her deſire and endeavour was, Not to remain alway under the power of them. She her ſelf would not take the righteouſneſs of the righteous from him for one failing, but would ſtill have a charity and good word for good people, even when they had diſobliged her. God and men judg of men and women, not as they are ſometime in a <hi>Paroxiſm,</hi> or a tranſport of paſſion, but according as the pulſe of their ſouls beats conſtantly towards God and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. We read in the Book of <hi>Job, Will the Hypocrite pray always?</hi> That is, He will not pray always. And
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34089:13"/>again, <hi>The hope of the hypocrite is like the ſpiders web, and like the giving up of the Ghoſt: but the righteous hath hope in his death.</hi> We may conclude hence, then, That your Daughter had hope in her death; and that your Ladiſhip is not to mourn for her, as one without hope. When her Father-in-law, coming to viſit her the day before ſhe dyed, ſaid, <hi>Daughter, I hope all will be well,</hi> (meaning a ſafe delivery from the pains of Child-birth) ſhe replied, <hi>It will be best, or better for me, if I dye.</hi> And if it be conſidered how ſhe offered up ſtrong cryes and prayers, with tears, in her extremity, to him that was able to pardon and ſave her; we need not doubt, but conclude, That as ſhe lived God's Servant, ſo ſhe dyed his Servant; and not a jot the leſs for her judging and condemning her ſelf for a grievous ſinner, and with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> for the worſt of ſinners; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the conſtant courſe of her life for many years, approved her ſelf none of the leaſt of Saints.</p>
            <p>We have better evidence of her being ſaved, than that ſhe dyed in Child-bed: nor, again, is it any evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that ſhe wanted ſaving-faith, becauſe ſhe dyed in Child-bed: for we read in Scripture but of two Women who dyed in Child-bearing, and they were both godly Women, <hi>viz. Rachel,</hi> the beloved Wife of the Patriarch <hi>Jacob;</hi> and the Wife of <hi>Phineas</hi> the Prieſt, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.19. Nor had ſhe only the Graces of a good Woman, but I may ſay of her, as a Noble Lord ſaid many years ſince of her dear Siſter, (now alſo with God) That ſhe had three good properties of a good Wife: <hi>She was fruitful,</hi> and <hi>frugal,</hi> and <hi>loving to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</hi> She was ſo good and kind a Mother to her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that many thought her too good: Sure I am, That it could not be charged upon her, as it is upon ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34089:14"/>That <hi>they are without natural affection;</hi> or that <hi>her heart was hardened toward her young.</hi> I rather ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that if all young women had been like her, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would hardly have given it in charge to <hi>Timothy,</hi> to leſſon old women to teach the young ones to love their Children.</p>
            <p>To conclude her Character, as to her Verues and Graces, I may ſay of her, She pondered God's Word with the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> Believed, with the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Canaan;</hi> was Charitable and Pious, with <hi>Mary Magdalen;</hi> Attending to Preaching, with <hi>Lydia:</hi> and to come to her own Family, let me ſay, She had the Courage and Piety of her Grandfather, the Lord <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio Vere,</hi> Baron of <hi>Tilbury:</hi> the Charity and Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of her Father, Sir <hi>Roger Townſhend:</hi> the Zeal of her Brother, Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> for God, good men, and good Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Madam,</hi> with your Favour, let me tell them that never ſaw her face, if this Paper ever come to their hands, That her Soul dwelt in a decent habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and that her Picture (if ſhe would have been prevailed with to have ſate, (as was deſired by her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-law, and Husband, a little before her lying in) would have been a good Picture, and ſome comfort (though a ſhadow in compariſon) to her Friends and Children. It is the obſervation of an ingenuous perſon, That though in the Old Teſtament expreſs notice be taken of the Beauty of many Women, as of <hi>Sarah, Rebecca, Rachel,</hi> &amp;c. yet in the New-Teſtament, no mention is made of the fairneſs of any Woman, not becauſe they wanted, (ſaith my Author) but becauſe Grace is the Goſpel-beauty. And ſo, <hi>Madam,</hi> let me conclude her Character: She was a Gentlewoman of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34089:14"/>great Parts, of a very quick Wit, of a ready Tongue and Pen; few Women, to my knowledg, equalled her; and I knew not any, in theſe things, that excelled her. She was a Gentlewoman of Perſon ſufficiently fair, amiable, and comely; but yet her greateſt perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, beauty, and excellency, was more than a skin-deep Fairneſs.</p>
            <p>And thus, Madam, I have adventured (or eſſayed, at leaſt) to give your Ladiſhip a Character of your Daughter, Mrs. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> and therein (I hope) no ſmall ground of comfort for your great loſs; becauſe the greater is your loſs, the greater is her gain. And further, Let it be ſome alleviation to your Ladiſhip's ſorrow, That as ſhe lived not <hi>undeſired,</hi> ſo ſhe dyed not <hi>unlamented.</hi> Your Honour hath many in divers Orbs, that ſympathize with you in this Loſs. Whilſt ſhe was in her Pains, ſhe had the Cares, Prayers, and Tears, of her Husband, Father, Friends, and Servants, about her; and after her death, hath been lamented by her Relations at home, and Acquaintance and Strangers abroad.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> It is likely a matter of ſorrow and grief to your Ladiſhip, to think how her Sun ſet at Noon, that ſhe dyed in the midſt of her days; that the <hi>Pains</hi> of <hi>Child birth,</hi> ended in the <hi>Pangs</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> and that the <hi>Childs entrance</hi> into the World, was ſo near accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the <hi>Mothers exit,</hi> or going out of it. Again, That ſhe left the World, without leaving a Son behind her; and the rather too, becauſe ſhe had four Sons gone to Heaven before her. It may poſſibly add to your ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, That in reſpect of her frequent breedings of Children, and oft-times hard bringings forth of them into the World, and her burying of Eight of Eleven,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34089:15"/>before ſhe dyed, your Ladiſhip may look on her while ſhe lived, as not unacquainted with ſorrows: Yet, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> let not your heart be too much troubled; believe in God, who hath ſaid. <hi>All things ſhall work together for good, to them that love God, and are the called accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his purpoſe;</hi> That all things were ordered con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning her and hers, by an All-wife and All-good God and Father: and judg, <hi>Madam,</hi> by the premiſed Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, That her School of <hi>Affliction</hi> was to her a School of <hi>Inſtruction:</hi> and know, <hi>Madam,</hi> that any degree of any Grace which ſhe got by ſufferings, were it <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Humility, Self-denial, Contentation</hi> with her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and the trial of theſe were more precious than Gold; that Spiritual life is beyond Corporal, Eternal beyond Temporal, and her gain of Heaven makes a full amends for her fore-going of Earth.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>Madam,</hi> let it be a comfort to your Ladiſhip to remember, that your Daughter dyed not Childleſs; that ſhe leſt two Daughters, and one of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Mary,</hi> of ſuch Age, Perſon, and Parts, that (with God's bleſſing) ſhe may make you, within a few years, a happy and a joyful <hi>Great-Grandmother.</hi> Be pleaſed, <hi>Madam,</hi> further to conſider, That though none of your Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Male-Children lived to ſurvive their Mother; yet the holy Scriptures make mention of the Names of Sons and Daughters; of Daughters, as well as of Sons: and again, that <hi>Job</hi>'s three Daughters are expreſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred in the Holy Hiſtory, after his Reſtauration; when as the Names of his Sons are never menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, (as to ſatisfie your Ladiſhip for this particular) 'Tis obſerved by the Learned, That whereas <hi>Job,</hi> in concluſion, had his other Subſtance, or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34089:15"/>Goods, doubled to what it was before, he had only the ſame number of Seven Sons, and Three Daughters. Again, His other Subſtance they account was periſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, once loſt, and ever loſt; but his Children, being taken from Earth to Heaven, are not to be reputed loſt, but gone before: and let this leſſen your grief, That God did not cut off Root and Branch, Damm and Young, both in one day; but that this your Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child, ſo wonderfully ſaved, may in time to come live to comfort your Ladiſhip for the loſs of the Mother. Beſides, Madam, this ſad Providence may to your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip be an occaſion of, and motive to thankfulneſs, when you ſhall conſider the many great ſorrows, pains, and pangs, you have undergone, and the many and marvellous deliverances God hath wrought for you; that it was he alone that made you to differ herein from two of your Daughters, that turned your ſorrows into joy, that made you a living Mother of many li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and lively Children; and though he hath been pleaſed to take away ſome of your Children, (and who may ſay unto him, What doſt thou?) yet hath he left you others to comfort you; yea, few Ladies have ſuch a one to comfort them, as your Ladiſhip: God hath ſaid in his Providence to the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, the Lady <hi>VERE,</hi> your Ladiſhips Mother, the Root of that Noble Vine, <hi>Spare it, cut it not down, it hath a Bleſſing in it:</hi> He hath hitherto ſpared your Ladiſhip, the Body of the Tree, and hath left you ſtill many living and flouriſhing Branches, Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Childrens Children, to be under God the ſtay and ſtaff of your Age, and your Joy and Crown in the day of your Hoary-head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> In all that hath befallen your Family, let
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34089:16"/>this ſatisfie, That <hi>God hath given, and God hath taken away;</hi> and this, though laſt, let it not be the leaſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration to comfort you in theſe ſad and bad dayes wherein we live, That all thoſe of your Children who have been married, and ſo God hath joined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be Man and Wife, none but God hath ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated.</p>
            <p>And ſo praying God (He who comforteth them that are caſt down) <hi>to raiſe you up, and ſweeten this and all other your bitter Cups to you; and in all your ſaddeſt hours whilſt you are here below, to ſend you the Comforter, the Holy Ghoſt, from above,</hi> I humbly take leave,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours humble Servant, <hi>THOMAS HODGES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
